all right well have a bit of a surprise
for you to begin with and I suppose if
you're ready there we go okay Pizza
Limburg we are now recording a podcast
and that little thing happens with the
invisible crowd in the room and all of
and immediately there we go okay you're
back okay sweet
well peter lindbergh i've thought of an
interesting way to begin this and if you
don't mind I'd love to read out the
first two paragraphs from the excellent
article you co-authored with Connor
Barnes is that okay with you it all
right let's do it this is my audition to
do the full audio reading later on and
this article is called the mimetic
Tribes of culture war 2.0 how their rise
made infighting the norm and how we can
navigate the resulting culture war now
medium tells me this is a thirty-eight
minute read but Eric and I can do the
first couple paragraphs in write a
minute and a fucking half so all right
here we go until the last few years it
made sense to talk in terms of a red
tribe and a blue tribe when describing
political affiliation in the US the red
tribe was right-wing populist
nationalist religious concerned by
terrorism and valued sexual purity the
blue tribe was left-wing globalist
internationalist secular concerned by
global warming and valued sexual freedom
they had fundamental disagreements about
what America or the West was what it
needed to become and how to get there
they even had a culture war however the
red-blue dichotomy no longer provides a
sufficient map of the political
territory we find ourselves in enter
mimetic tribes we define a memetic tribe
as a group of agents with a Meem complex
or memeplex
that directly or indirectly seeks to
impose its distinct map of reality along
with its moral imperatives on others
these tribes are on active duty in the
new culture war they possess a
multiplicity of competing claims
interests goals and organizations while
the red and blue tribes were certainly
far from monolithic any claim to unity
between mimetic
is laughable an establishment leftist
who squabbles with the right-wing with
the rights must contend with mockery
from the dirtbag left
meanwhile the dirtbag left enjoys
critiques from social justice activists
SJS who in turn are criticized by the
intellectual dark web IDW the trench
warfare of the old culture war has
become an all-out brawl there we go I
think that's I think there's a really
nice and tight opening paragraphs there
so I wonder me if to begin with you
could tell our listeners a little bit
about yourself and what your interests
are and perhaps what motivated you to
co-author this article right right first
off I think I am gonna hire you to read
the audio book if it ever gets released
so yeah I appreciate that about myself
so I organized this group called
intellectual Explorers Club here in
Toronto and it's kind of a group that is
meant to explore ideas with maximum
charity and kind of expand our current
map of reality right and how we do that
we engage in book clubs debates lectures
and just have kind of you know
spitballing type conversations and put
ourselves at the edge of our thinking
because that's sort of like a
scintillating activity for myself is to
put myself at the edge of my thinking
and it really was sort of started off as
a selfish project for me to create this
group because I took philosophy and when
I was a university student and I
hungered to get this intellectual
engagement back in my life so I created
these this group but then it kind of
transcended that purpose a little bit
and inspired me to engage in I guess
collective sense making because when I
was the host and facilitator of these
these groups know when I still happens
today
there's just fragmented kind of almost
schizophrenic feeling I get because all
these people are just shouting their
reality tunnels their ideologies or
philosophies and I'm trying to contain
it all and at the same time to still
a dialogue to get everyone sort of level
set of what we're doing here what we're
talking about mm-hmm and that experience
of being a host and facilitator at these
in-person clubs inspired me
partly to write this paper and my
co-author Connor Barnes we sort of
geeked out on the political culture
where stuff for a while now yeah and we
recognize there's like multiple what we
called mimetic tribes or sort of
different ways to review a view culture
and reality not just what it is but what
it should be um
and what we dubbed culture war 1.0 it
was sort of had this notion that all
there's a left and then there's a right
and then they're fighting each other
yeah and I think that's a little bit too
simplistic of a narrative yes well and
so we've moved on to culture war 2.0
where we have a whole bunch of competing
tribes which are calling mean tribes or
is it mimetic tribes which is a slightly
partial word for mean tribe of course
but yeah and look that seems appropriate
and that seems fitting I think how many
what percentage of human beings and then
you have to pull this figure completely
out of nowhere of course what percentage
of human beings consume memes on a daily
basis it's like it's a good but if you
have access to a screen you're
essentially consuming memes all day long
and and that memes in the in the graphic
type we of course know and love memes
meaning ideas or perhaps what like ideas
that are that that sort of create or are
part of your sense making lens that
replicate themselves of course are more
ubiquitous phenomenon and our part of
the sort of frameworks we use to make
sense of the world so we've moved on to
culture Ward 2.0 how would you say
that's defined in contrast to culture
war 1.0 right so I think the idea of
culture war 1.0 which was prevalent in
the the early 90s with the pati
Buckhannon and the idea of the religious
right trying to kind of impose a
religious narrative a Christian
narrative on the American culture and it
being pushed back by the secular left
so there is this idea that there was to
a left and a right competing with each
other but I imagined there was it was
fragmented as well but it just wasn't
salient given the media landscape at the
time yes but thanks thanks to the the
internet were sort of like exposed to
all these ideas mm-hmm and I really like
the metaphor of the the noosphere like
viewing kind of the at least the
infrastructure and the hardware of the
Internet as a brain and then the content
that's floating around it the means that
are flowing and floating around in it as
this big collective mind yes and
currently this collective mind is
fragmented its disagreement is combative
all that type of stuff yeah and so I
guess that's the answer your question
the key distinction is sort of this
fragmentation is more salient now and
when people on the Left just call
everyone like you know everyone's a Nazi
or this but if you kind of zoom in on
that container of what some people
consider the right there's very little
good disagreement amongst all these
different kind of segments they might
have broad coalition and they have might
have broad agreement but their
infighting may be more so than they're
out fighting right yeah of course yeah
one of the particular invites you
mentioned is between the alt-right and
the old light so that all right of
course don't like the old light for
trying to what limit some of their
claims to do with I suppose the old riot
is genuinely typifies by Wow all of a
sudden move to walk it into this
territory to have to formalize my
thoughts on it in a way that's coherent
well there typifies by that kind of
ethno nationalist tendency and they take
that ethnic group identity very
seriously in a way that for everyone
else is some mixture of terrifying and
incorrect or at least irrelevant when it
comes to genuinely partitioning or
recognizing the value in human beings
and of course they don't like the old
light I mean not you often I suppose
hate what you see as the turncoats
in your side more than anything else
which is of course we see a phenomenon
we see on the left as well and someone
like christina hoff sommers identifying
as a feminist getting absolutely railed
against by the more radical feminists
and just recently she's actually been
over here in Australia and I didn't
attend the talks but I heard that she
was received very poorly too many jeers
from the crowd
clare lehman the editor and founder of
quill let made a post to this nature on
twitter sort of decrying the lack of
good intellectual faith she was met with
in australia and in particular by you
know feminists that from a broad-brush
you would take as part of the same tribe
but certainly aren't of course and you
have fights between the intersectional
feminists and other kinds of feminists
so we have this fracturing and I have
this this definition here of memetic
tribes that you give in the article and
you define mimetic tribes as a group of
agents with amine complex mean flex that
directly seeks to impose its distinct
map of reality along with its moral
imperatives on others right and the goal
is to win the culture war or at least
not to lose so an important change you
might say open if it's not a change just
a bringing to articulations something
that might always have been the case to
some degree amongst human beings which
is that rather than just a political
position there are immediate moral
imperatives moral attitudes associated
and moral judgments associated with your
identification to any one of these
tribes which is one of the things that
makes conversation really really
difficult because as soon as you get a
little trigger that someone belongs to
this tribe or that tribe whether it's
the color of their hair or who they
listen to on a podcast all of a sudden I
presume something even physiological
happens you know you maybe get flood of
this sympathetic response in the nervous
system and it's like oh shit this is a
motherfucker like I went into a bar the
other day where we recorded an event a
conversation which will be out soon
I went back in there to talk to the
manager and thanked him and asked if I
could use his voice but appeared quit
and they were like yeah when you put
this event on that was a thing that did
it for him and he quit after that was
that is that joke I'm not sure if it is
but anyway this this um you know lady
behind the bar was wearing a t-shirt
that was down with the patriarchy or
something like this and we had a nice
interaction but then I mentioned the
t-shirt you know and I was thinking what
tone of voice do I need to use here so I
can mention the patriarchy or something
like this without it causing like some
kind of attrition that would stop her
stop this interaction and I said well
what comes after the patriarchy but you
know I have a private-school accent from
England so generally speaking if I was
to say something like what comes off the
patriarchy it might be understood as
some kind of conflict you know and she
turned away and there was he felt like
that little bit of tension there and she
wasn't willing to continue the
interaction so you have to find some
ways of of bridging or speaking to ways
of relating to someone who might be very
very critical of someone who doesn't
let's say embody the right memes present
the right memes to be taken as part of
the tribe so that you can have a certain
kind of conversation now interestingly
I'm pretty sure you've identified the
kinds of people who wish to do this as
having their own tribe is that right in
the article we written or I'm not I'm
not showing that article I think later
like I'm interested in your in your
labeling of it's the metagame I mean if
they've got they've got a concept of
memetic mediators right right but I
wonder if yeah I mean what we're seeing
I suppose is some network of people
emerge who are willing to have these
kinds of conversations and then you know
you got to be careful
I suppose that it doesn't become a tribe
of its own in some sense although maybe
it's not such a big deal right yeah I
wanna I definitely want to double click
on the metagame but to briefly circle
back on that
dorium down with the patriarchy sure sir
sure that that person was wearing just
to share my own similar story when I was
in a coffee shop recently there's this
girl she had this tattoo said that God
is a girl right and then I said hey uh
how come guard God is not a woman right
I said that that's kind of a playful
little yeah that's good and then she and
then she thought like oh I thought you
were going to say why God's not a man
and I was gonna be like ooh and then she
got really kind of like angry right now
but in that in also in a sort of a
subtly playful way and then and then I
got my my coffee then I'm like you know
what - Timm choir into that why should
you assume that I was going to say God
is a man right and and then so I engaged
in sort of like a meta communication
about the communication that just
occurred and we actually had like a
really great conversations like huh I
did I don't know why that that's the
first thing that came to my head and
then we just kind of engaged further and
we had a good chat and I like this idea
of meta communication and this lends
itself is mitigating the idea that you
can kind of step out of sort of the game
that you're playing the finite game that
you're playing and then see all the
other type of finite games and have a
conversation about it in a sort of a
non-judgmental way yes yes no I think
that's I think that's an excellent idea
and you know on the ground level that
takes a lot of I would say skill when it
comes to being able to identify what are
the trigger points really for people and
their particular mean plexes but in
another sense and and I don't really
approach things like that when I when I
get about and talk to people I would
switch out which I do quite a lot and
and in fact I actually have an event
coming up I haven't put it online yet
but the posters are up at the venue it's
not going to be recorded and it's going
to be a step into trying to be this role
of I can say it to you I wouldn't I'm
not going to say it out loud exactly to
people at the event of you trying to be
a memetic mediator here but between you
and I and our listeners I suppose we'll
be having this event titled ego self
masculinity and femininity
together a panel of people and I'm gonna
have a wireless mic and can try and set
up the space of this bar so that there
is sort of a circular facing or it's
kind of like a long rectangle but people
sitting on the perimeter be having a
conversation and an interactive forum
just having people express what
masculinity and femininity mean to them
and to attempt to create this container
where it is about this Co exploration
where most importantly what is valued
well a few a few things are valued but
but one important thing for our purposes
right now is the belief in the dignity
of the human spirit just the idea that
there's something fundamental about all
of us that has value and it's at am this
more fundamental existential perhaps
even spiritual level where we are
ultimately connected and where some
important source of our value is derived
from and and I think you know and I can
speak a little bit about what I mean
about that perhaps now or another time
but but I think there's something about
embodying that place of connection and a
genuine goodwill towards other human
beings like a real embodiment of that
that I believe at least I hope in many
cases certainly believe for a lot of
them that it's possible to conduct
interactions from this place and have
that be a way to I mean disarm might be
a you know a functional word here but I
certainly find some way to talk to the
part in someone that's really willing to
relate authentically and but
nevertheless depending on when the the
particulars of a given person and how
receptive they are for dialogue perhaps
the state of their nervous system to
some degree you might have to really
make sure not to tread on the wrong the
wrong land the wrong landmines and so
you can begin this kind of discussion
but I think it's a really worthwhile
endeavor and I would invite everyone
listening right now to to follow you and
all the things you post about it there's
a couple other people in this network
who have got really good ideas and who
are really tackling this question or
of how to genuinely have effective
meaningful conversations on the ground
given the context of this culture war
2.0 which is something we're really only
beginning to get to to grips with
in my opinion right right and I like
that I like that idea that you're doing
that in-person event because I think
that the topic of masculinity especially
is is a trigger worthy on many fronts
right right it's like I like the term
that the meta modernist use a
philosophical allergies right and that
we're toxic masculinity or just
masculine itself is such a such a word
that has so much emotional weight into
it so that's a good topic to engage in
the medic mediation with and then just
to touch on that point that you made
about kind of the spirit of engagement
and it's like you know you can get this
would kind of separates mean what I
think I'm doing from sort of like the
the rationalist or the the more
atheistic tribes how they're really
concerned with the truth and objective
truth and getting things right yeah I do
think that is important but when it
comes to dialogue I'm more interested in
the act of understanding hmm all right
it's like just shine a light on your map
of reality and just understand it as
best as I can and I'm probably gonna get
it wrong I'm probably gonna stumble it's
probably gonna be messy but just that
spirit of understanding I think people
feel that and it's just arming and then
it's like okay the fight-or-flight
response is not being enacted right now
yes person it means goodwill and this
type of talk yeah and I think regardless
from my experience engaging with many
different people that are belong to
these these medic tribes you can engage
in dialogue if you come in with that
spirit or you contain or you create a
container you know a modality or in
person kind of framework that allows for
100% I mean well what do we like in
interactions with people we like oh we
bloody like to be heard I think on some
level we we like to know and feel that
in some sense
something that's authentic to us about
what we want to achieve is is in
principle it's like it's on the table
for good development it's on the table
it's on the table for growth when we're
coming into a relationship someone with
someone it's it's more meaningful if a
part of us that's really willing to grow
and develop is is in touch is is
activated and and it's kind of being
reciprocal II realized with someone
right and this can take place in an an
intellectual conversation but but for
the some of the reasons we've discussed
that that that part of your moral
identity can be tied into political
beliefs and various political signals
given the fragmentation of culture and
various crises we're facing yeah it
becomes important that where you where
where your comprehension of virtue sits
that that's being that that's being
heard that that's being understood I
mean to get somewhere jointly you might
want to go you first have to try and
understand where someone is so I totally
I totally agree with you and then you
know the ideal of course is once you can
co develop that that container that's
something really quite productive could
be done with it and I know that stuff
that excites both of us quite a lot and
is part of the yeah part of there's a
couple memes out there collective
intelligence and coming into flow States
in conversation this this whole notion
of collective sense making that we're
seeing play out online with channels and
podcasts like rebel wisdom and satellite
thinkers to the IDW like Jordan Hall and
Jamie wheel and some of these guys
really getting involved in trying to
have productive conversations about well
the first thing is to get clear on
precisely where we are so it's about
coming into that you know understanding
and so then we might figure out and
connect to yeah what is healthy and asks
what is good in us
can connect and imagine the world in a
way that represents the world accurately
enough so that effective decisions can
be taken and executed within it and it
must start with understanding I totally
agree and the way you said there but the
values and we listed on that white paper
and that sort of that spreadsheet that I
recommend your listeners check out the
spreadsheet that lists all the medic
tribes and they're sort of like their
taxonomy and then we said that we label
it the sacred values right and and I
think a lot of these in tribes and
people it's like their sacred values are
always at threat and they're always like
need to be ready to defend them mm-hmm
and so if you shine a light and say I'm
gonna understand your sacred value right
yeah it's almost like an act of love on
their sacred value yeah and then it sort
of opens the door says you know what
like I have a different sacred value and
let's have a discussion about it yeah
but sort of that that that move of
understanding and making sure you let
the other person know you understand
I think should come first if you want to
have that dialogue to take place yes yes
I think it's I think it's absolutely
critical so what I did yesterday is I
took myself out and I went through that
article and I went through some of your
recent tweets and I have here a list of
that's my fucking research so I have
here a list of items that all of which I
think we could discuss for quite some
time and I think we've set the stage now
decently well enough I mean before I
touched on any of these I might ask you
because I think how many mean tribes do
you identify is it like 20 on the
spreadsheet there's a lot right but then
there's smaller main ones as more than
20 maybe even yeah I think there's 32
that we listed but of course there's
many more yeah that you know I got
introduced to after writing that paper
for example the meta modernists I was
somewhat aware of them but I didn't
realize that they were bigger than they
actually were and they really dig the
paper and they reached out to me so
that's one that I
would include if I were to rewrite that
but yeah we listed 32 yeah cool what are
the most relevant ones for the current
war would you say who I would say the
social justice activists the
intellectual darkweb and maybe some of
the the old right out light type tribes
yeah you also have the the dynamic of
the establishment left and right as well
which play a very interesting role still
because you would say they're the ones
that are pulling the reigns of
mainstream media and so really for a
large percentage of the population and
still in some sense look if the world
really was burning I would look at
Reddit and then once reddit had
basically convinced me I probably still
I'd still try and find a news article
that was from one of the you know one of
the mainstream media outlets and be like
okay so I even though even though
there's a lot of criticism you know the
mainstream media is dead and
what-have-you it's like there's still
something maybe for our generation I
think part of our collective psyche
still has a an affinity for these for
these institutions and in some sense the
part of frustration I mean when you see
people like Eric Weinstein he's been
tweeting recently you ever see him and
Brett tweet all the time and they're
very much involved in saying things when
there are particularly egregious
articles written and published in the
big establishment institutions that you
would hope for more from whether it's
The Economist or the New York Times
there's still this sense of many people
want to save what they see as a decline
in institutional credibility so I think
that establishment left/right mean tribe
dichotomy there is still very relevant
and I would say for people that don't
engage online as much or really take it
as seriously I think opinions are still
very much informed by these by these
places
here's an interesting one as well you've
got and I know you mentioned this it's
the the the I forget the name of the
tribe but it's the one that Alex Jones
is the creator that the key player for
now you don't call it this but it's
gotta be it's got its that mixture of
schizophrenic tendencies tendency
conspiracy theorists and it's like no
one realized how many of those
motherfuckers they really were like he's
got a pretty big audience and he paints
her he paints a very very interesting
picture and the reality is is that of
course we've seen different instances
with pizza gay and other things like
that where real physical consequences
have taken place because of because of
this kind of what spastic sense making
some sense so but there's a lot there's
many there's many more you mentioned and
the Jordan Peterson sorters that's why
and I've you know the centrists and
classical liberal centrist types sort of
fall into that category and and then you
have the part of the left that's
critical of let's say that SJS but still
take themselves to be let's say rescuing
what they see as the kina less
understood Marxist points so they might
be very very critical of capitalism and
think that just a pure rejection of
anything socialist based on taking what
they would see as historically misc
ill-conceived and ill implemented
versions of Marxism or socialism or
what-have-you as being an ineffective
analysis or and actually will given the
problems with capitalism we need some
sort of hybrid and it falls more towards
a socialist side and how dare you stop
the conversation here because look at
all this exploitation on the capitalist
side of things and that's a very big
you know that's a that's a very big
tribe to so great and it's like I think
you did a nice job of describing all
this sort of fragment
and all these reality tunnels that are
sort of coexisting in this this
noosphere and I like that ken wilber
quote is that no one's smart enough to
be a hundred percent wrong right and
even the the wildly conspiracy
conspiracy tribes like you went on right
there like deeply looking at the deep
state and nobody else is really looking
at them as deep as they are yeah they
might stumble on something that no one
else is stumbling upon because they're
looking at it yeah so such intensity
yeah and so I kind of like the idea of
just kind of being charitable and seeing
first of all recognizing what they're
saying on their own terms and seeing
what I could take from that yeah you
know yeah yeah and then to mention the
whole kind of right left I caught a me
and I should say with this article right
off the bat and then kind of any other
mimetic artifacts that I intend to
create I'm basing it off or I'm inspired
by the post rationalist there's tribe
called the post rationalists and they
they kind of operate on this motto of
it's better to be interesting and wrong
than right and boring right because
being interesting and wrong sets up
other people inspires other people to
pursue truth or rightness continue the
conversation guys continuing this
infinite game of most of the public
conversation keeping it alive and so
with this the white paper what we did
called mimetic tribes and culture were
2.0 which is the the crux premise there
is you know we're living in a fragmented
culture war I'm not to attach that that
idea yes it's just sort of interesting
enough that hasn't really been presented
in the way we presented it that be
created this this dialogue that it did
around it but I do think there's a lot
of validity and a need for this kind of
like just general right left economy yes
and you know before the the idea of the
right left was like okay right was it
about small government left was big
government and now they said it was like
right it was about open borders closed
borders which I don't think is you know
you can necessarily divide that to right
or left because there's you know there's
left-wing populist and right-wing
populist
but one thing that I find interesting at
least in the culture war setting is this
sort of what I like to label where I'm
currently labeling the the woke
coalition right right and the coalition
consists of social justice activists
which you know some people call the
social justice warriors black life
matters me too and then the other
coalition is what i when i'm currently
dubbing that the red pill coalition
right and this consists of the alt-right
the old lights the manosphere and all
the masculine tribes and then you've got
this sort of like this the centrist
intellectual darkweb sorters you know
the optimists that they're kind of like
in between this nebulous space they're
trying to push back on both but they're
it's funny the the woke tribes view them
as like a gateway drug to the red pill
and the red pill tribes view them as
some useful 80s to this global
conspiracy or whatever globalist
conspiracy yeah so they're they're not
getting love from any of the sides but I
view the culture whereas this woke
coalition red pill coalition and the
centrist in the middle yeah and I think
that's that's fair you know to say this
is existing yeah and then what I'm
flirting with this idea of flirting with
is that maybe it's a political movement
maybe it's not but there's like if you
have that spectrum that political
spectrum of you know left woke red pill
right and then centrist in the middle
then there's this meta category right
above it floating above it right yeah
the high book yeah yeah yeah and I can
you can you're you could have a
temperament or you can have sacred
values that maybe resonate with all kind
of these buckets but then you could also
be meta you can also be a meta gamer
right it's almost like a liminal state a
cognitive liminal state that you can
visit mm-hmm yeah cool well I think the
meta game is great and look when I when
I first came across your article I came
across it through a link that Jordan
Hall put to it in his 2019 AOC update
and I'd actually quite like to do a
reading of that and release that as well
because that's also another brilliant
article and Jordan Hall I can't
recommend his writing on medium enough
but when I when I read your article I
was like this is really good
this articulates things that are helpful
and it sort of clued on to the memes of
the times
but I did think you know there's always
gonna be a little disagreement about
precisely what you're capturing in each
category and some of them might be like
you know does that qualify as a category
and many of people of course belong to
multiple and I know that's something
you'd you know you wouldn't you wouldn't
reject a tool and so the point would
just be something like yes we these are
you know maybe only relatively few are
actually to be honest some of those some
of those categories are so big in the
culture war is so entrenched that
actually some people's identities do
seem to be almost entirely within one
camp however even in that case these
camps aren't fundamental categories of
human being right there are deeper
existential realities to what we are and
and and you know it's it's very much a
cultural political level of analysis
that's important for to to sort of
understand engage current cultural
dialogue but the other thing is is that
of course we we have these aspects of
our sad are deeper and and crosscut with
the affinities of many of these groups
and it's relating on that level that is
well we sort of covered that before when
it comes to understanding that it's the
intellectual part of that in terms of
what are your sacred memes but then
there's also this dropping into that
space and people talk about it as
liminal space and I think that's a fine
word I think there are other words do
you use to describe it I'd probably I
probably prefer something slightly more
existential II sort of poetically minded
we can drop into this space of shared
relationship with each other very much
takes place in that moment there and
that becomes and is the most real thing
and we can we can we sort of intuitively
map on these different kind of patterns
that enable us to come into communion
with each other in in more effective
ways so I guess it's you know it's
probably unnecessary to stress but in
fact it let me stress it for us that
these aren't meant to these categories
aren't meant to trap people in them you
know quite quite the contrary however
nevertheless the idea of the virtue of
the metagame
playing the metagame which I mean if I'm
if I'm getting you right to put it into
other words would be something like yeah
the capacity to recognize the the values
in different tribes and to incorporate
other levels of analysis that look to
explain the rise of this kind of
tribalistic phenomenon altogether so
maybe taking evolutionary theory maybe
existential philosophical theory maybe
some kind of spiritual approach where
you're looking to understand the
proclivities within individuals that
have them aligned with these different
tribes not just proclivities within
individuals but also conditions of the
time and economic conditions of the time
and technological changes of the time
and different crises we're facing that
might put pressure on people to be part
of one group or another and so the idea
is that in separating oneself from an
affinity with one particular memeplex
let's say you're able to recognize how
those different parts of a fractured
culture might actually be won
maneuvering hole that is worthy of love
in all its areas and worthy of tending
to now something flagged up so I'm going
on a bit of a ramble here but like part
of what flagged up there is like some
people be like well what about those old
right types are what about those real
radical leftist communist types are they
worthy of love too it's like yeah
actually in some important sense they
have to be that doesn't mean you endorse
what their propositions are or endorse
what their actions are like far from it
you can put a hard note to that but that
there is a human being to understand
they're right that there is something
about that proclivity and about that
position in society that is reflective
of a broader phenomenon that's that must
be understood and so infants from an
input importance sense must be related
to it must be really held right must not
just be forced away so that you're not
paying attention to it and not really
trying on to understand it yes you have
to look at it with some sort of open
mind so you can at least get clear on
what the on what the current map is
we're working with otherwise how on
earth could you hope to fit it too
the territory or what the territory
should be mm-hmm it's like a lot of
threads that can go down there um you
know I'm currently flirting with a pen
and theistic view of God right now and
you know that's the idea that you know
God is reality right and so if you if
you love God and you love reality and
everything that reality consists of and
then all these different individuals or
these tribes they have a map of reality
right and so in a way understanding
their map of reality is loving that map
of reality and not that's to say that
your greeing with it or you think is
accurate or you think it's right or
moral or all that type of stuff but this
is having putting some understanding to
it I think is a useful useful exercise
and sort of what I like is sort of
having a map of maps right right so this
is cultivating a map of all the the
various maps of reality out there all
right andin let's say if somebody is
truly evil or needs to be stopped you
know like it's like some soon like you
know your enemy know yourself know your
enemy but if you have this kind of
cartoonish version of your enemy you
don't really understand them then you
can't really even effectively fight them
mm-hmm so there's on multiple levels I
think is an important exercise to have
an accurate understanding of somebody
else's map of reality yeah 100% all
right so here's a couple of interesting
things we might do I've got I've written
down each of the six crises that you
recognized in the article so we could
talk about those but you know perhaps
and you know what perhaps actually
perhaps actually we'll come back to that
because I want to because you mentioned
the blue pill and the red pill before
which of course comes from the matrix
and is has definitely entered popular
culture and I'm in a major way right and
it's like the red pill has being the
thing that wakes you up from the matrix
or the status quo that was
you know in us this state of illusion so
the red pill is this this the shot of
disillusionment but the thing is about
the red pill is that it doesn't
necessary to cool or something you might
recognize that hey the emperor has no
clothes like there's something real
strange about what's going on here and
actually I feel more in touch with
what's really real given I understand
this world from this new perspective but
what happens then right because you know
what matrix have you just woken up into
that you think is real because it's
differentiated from your previous matrix
but strings are always being pulled by
something it seems to me and and enter
here what if I'm right might be if you
want to continue with this metaphor of
pill taking we have the gray pill right
so maybe you could describe to me what
the gray pill is right this this pill
territory is you know it's like
confusing confusing ground because some
groups co-opted some groups understand
it differently yeah you're right it
started it started with the matrix
the blue pill is sort of like you
maintain the reality that you currently
understand and then the the red pill
you're shot into the truth and then you
know the the what I said there the red
pill the the right the reactionary right
they kind of really co-opted this meme
of the red pill and I think it started
with the manosphere or the the men's
rights activists and then it kind of got
enlarged to the alt light I'll write and
then neo reactionaries but this thing
that the crux of it like the red pill
being awoken to the truth you can say
the woke tribes have that's that's their
version of the red pill being woke to
the systemic discrimination of society
that's being red pill yeah right yeah
and then in addition to this those the
dissident right they're reactionary
right they really seem to run with this
pill metaphor so there's like the blue
pill there's the red pill there
black pill and he's just so nihilistic
and now there's just something called
the hunk pill like a hunk pill good
which I we can maybe that's a rabbit
hole we can get down into but then when
we wouldn't I mentioned they're great
pill in the article is actually the near
post rationalist tribe Venkatesh Rao
from Ribbon Farm he coined that term and
he basically said that you know we're
born into the blue pill we don't
actually take a blue pill we're just
born into everyday reality sure and then
there's a multitude of different red
pills that we take that cannot make us
see the truth but then the gray pill
sort of muddies the waters a little bit
it adds uncertainty to the mix it adds
nuance right and then that could lead to
an existential crisis it can lead to
confusion
but he argues and I tend to agree with
it in order to fully feel intellectually
alive is to start being comfortable with
being gray pills right yes yes yes no
absolutely
so really the great pill as well I just
hear there is the quite the quite
obvious if I can use that word quite
obvious point that sense-making
continues you know and you know and I
think many people will be very cognizant
of the nuance and uncertainty that is
very much a part of of our of our makeup
and the reality we confront so yes I do
think it's appropriate for for that
nuance that nuance to be in there good
good alright okay so let's see we've got
these six these six crises which are
still going to get to because I'm
interested in asking that this is some
of your recent tweets there's two terms
that came up I want you to explain to me
I don't know if they relate to each
other so I apologize if I'm chucking you
tangents here which I suppose I've been
doing anyway one is image sacrifice and
the other is cancel culture well what do
you mean by these things
okay this is this is my go down a rabbit
hole is that my edge of my think show
because when I tweet these things in
this moments of inspiration I'm just
kind of like barfing an idea yeah it's
totally speculation and I'm not
propositional II attached to it but are
you familiar with the idea of cancel
culture I read into a little bit after I
saw your tweet but no I couldn't
formulate it for you but it's probably
in there if you give me a little bit
I'll be I'll be with it's um
amongst the work tribes in mainstream
media is quite popular to use this
person has been cancelled yes if they
said something controversial if they
said something racist sexist and then
they're canceled right if we cancelled
from mainstream society plate Society
cancelled and then your cancels right
and then there's there's a lot of
pushback not only from like the right
sort of tries but also within the woke
tribes just pushed back on this like
Kanye West even though he got cancelled
by wearing that trump hat he's you know
he did the tweet we should cancel cancel
culture I think Katy Perry just did a
speech that we should be careful who we
can so we should be kind with
forgiveness yeah because the idea of
cancel culture you know you could just
really lose your your reputation
Rini reputation especially if the
accusation is not on verse and true and
you could also lose your livelihood with
that reputation right and so it's like
people feel like they're walking on
eggshells there Terrell that the moments
notice that could be canceled yeah yeah
and so and so from that idea I this is
my me at the edge of my thinking and the
crazy speculative thought is that cancel
culture kind of got detached from its
original purpose of maintaining purity
within the woke tribe and then they just
want to it's like a cancel God I like
the idea the cancel God got emerged and
the cancel God needs images to sacrifice
to be sacrificed to mmmm and then these
these sort of the red pill tribes are
playing with this like okay what can we
sacrifice what images can we sacrifice
to the cancel God now
okay let's sacrifice Pepe the Frog
it's kind of co-opted in making evil
let's coop the okay symbol and sacrifice
that let's coop clowns right and so just
viewing this as this kind of like this
god of cancellation emerge and they want
to cancel he wants to eat up celebrities
they want to eat up all kinds of images
yeah and they eat up culture itself and
maybe human life itself okay and so that
was sort of the idea I was speculating
with and so instead of human sacrifice
maybe the a need for image sacrifices
occurring ran out council water its to
pure pure we can only drink diluted
water we need that diversity in their
water molecule great right yeah that's
cool yeah I see I see that I mean
certainly it's the case that you get
runaway trains of people looking to be
of seeing outrage in different places
and look at the level of Twitter
following I have which is absolutely
minimal I've only had a very few things
occur but this was like a year and a
year a year ago now and I'd been sharing
at the time my own memes there a tribe
of one which were various you know
Jungian quotes attached to our work that
I liked and not just union quotes
different philosophical quotes and
what-have-you and just as I was going
through and researching for my
dissertation or just for my general
education was just sharing them out
there and I you know attracted a every
so often there'd be someone on Twitter a
couple people on Twitter who I would
notice would like a few posts in a row
and I'd be like oh they're digging home
that's cool you know this is how people
looking at this stuff and so but but you
know those people were not affiliated
with their ad and said anything
political and then I reach I retweeted a
tweet that I saw about the reforest
station of England and that actually
according to this article at some point
last year or it was scheduled to reach
reach in a few years I'm not exactly
sure England had or Great Britain had
got back to a place of forestation that
hadn't had for many hundreds of years it
was like a
thing you know like pay we've planted
that many trees too actually there's a
lot of trees about and we should be
happy about that and I just retweeted it
didn't say anything I was like yeah
that's cool right and this one this one
this woman just immediately responded
included me in a wither with a bunch of
other people and she just railed against
me for being a shield for oil companies
and things like this just immediately
immediately on on my back so yes look
you do see these things happen and of
course of course it's a very popular
thing that people look to see their own
little pet triggers activated their own
it's like affirms their worldview and
you can see how in some sense it gives
people security to label and find
genuine icons of yeah that affirm their
worldviews in these cases and sometimes
those icons are real but that this
runaway train of of this putting people
down this wanting to be that virtuous be
wanting to be that pure it's very
dangerous on the on the purity grounds
right when people start like I've heard
is spoken about the like a big player in
genocide I'm pretty sure is the
psychological measure of disgust disgust
sensitivity as a measure of
conscientiousness there's something I
think Jordan Peterson makes his point
when he talks about you know he read
mine mine Kampf Hitler's work and
studied the Nazis and made know of the
frequent usage of this Hitler is
mentioning how he wanted the Germans to
be a pure body and his references were
always to this theme of purity and what
violator that like and what do you do
with something that's that's impure what
do you do with vermin with you know
they're in your house you exterminate
them so it's and you can see how the
canceling
and the extermination I mean canceling
is very much like it's like the reality
TV version it's like somebody's tied
into this let's cancel them you know but
ya know I'm with you I think that's cool
I think I think that they're two times
that image sacrificing cancel culture I
think I think they're they're worthy
additions to this to this conversation
and this like just the really putting
myself at am I thinking right now and
might enter some poetic territory but
let's just say if this cancel culture
kind of gets detached from its original
purpose of sort of policing you know the
purity of the woke tribes and it's just
sort of like this hungry for should just
cancel for its own sake
right the camp I bought emerges right
and this culture war this is sort of
like confused soup that we're living in
it's really damaging our collective
sense making right and I like to view it
as an existential crisis that prevents
us from addressing other existential
crisis right and so while this cancel
God is canceling everything right it's
just kind of setting up us to be
cancelled as a human race right if we
don't address these existential threats
yeah so I'm trying to figure out how to
like maybe more linked up more
articulately and in an essay format but
that's sort of an idea that I'm playing
with yeah look where the idea I mean one
thing I would point to of course is that
there's many tendencies within us many
tendencies even staying within this
field of memetic identification into
these different tribes there are many
versions of those I think that are
setting us up to be cancelled right I
think if you take only the black pill
and fall into a some sort of nihilistic
spin then this is a problem and look
there's many nihilists out there to say
you don't understand nihilism Nilan
islands nihilism is actually
emancipatory because then once you
understand that there's no objective
meaning you know then you can just
create your own meaning and it's like
okay well there's a big conversation to
get into there I would say that most
people who embody nihilism do not engage
actively in a certain kind of meaning
making that is adaptive well over any
period of time apart from the immediate
short-term grass
vacation one but that's an interesting
conversation and we don't have to go
into that here I have big interest in
nihilism and in meaning and what have
you just spoke to John in Vevey icky
yesterday which had a really listened
conversation there I really enjoyed
John's appearance on your podcast so I
recommend everybody go listen to that on
the intellectual Explorers Club so I
hope to talk to John many more times I
think that was a really good
conversation and I think coming to
understand the meaning crisis and what
meaning is at a level that is requires
levels of analysis far beyond the the
cultural you know understanding
historical development of our cognition
and the metaphysical basis for reality
as such I think that's also involved as
well you have the physiological level
what it is to be in states of flow and
and and you want to talk about religion
and nutrition and all these kind of
things all of that folds into
understanding their felt phenomenon of
being in meaningful relationship with
but so okay so maybe that brings us to
these two these crises then and there
are six we have the secularization and
the meaning crisis we have the
fragmentation and the reality crisis we
have the atomization and the belonging
crisis we have the globalization and the
proximity crisis we have the stimulation
and sobriety crisis and we have the
weaponization and the warfare crisis now
you also do this really nice one-line
descriptions of each of these crises so
perhaps it's worth me just reading those
out to if that's alright with you and
then and then you know you can decide
what one you'd like to comment on mainly
because we won't have time to get to
them all and they're very very
interesting all of them so the meaning
crisis weakened our collective
understanding of what ought to be and
these are all quotes the reality crisis
fractured our collective understanding
of what is the belonging crisis took
away a genuine feeling of community the
proximity crisis removed distance from
conflicting views
the sobriety crisis reduced our agency
and turned us into addicts the warfare
crisis transformed our minds into
weapons for hidden Wars in plain sight
they're really ties depressing they're
really really tight they're really
really tight sentences there man and
having read the having read the article
a couple times it's um it's really
nicely it's really nicely analytically
derived from that from that other
writing so I really appreciate it thank
you thank you yeah just when you're
reading that out of like mr. pressing
Keys together and come up with some
other crises as well right as well it's
this is a good city to start with this
is some issues we have going on here
yeah I don't know how much I have to add
to that kind of that summary but it's
sort of like the the first to the
meaning crisis and the reality crisis
and I guess maybe the reality crisis
could have been dubbed the sense-making
crisis or the truth crisis sort of like
you know how each map of reality has
sort of an is in a nod yes right what a
descriptive a description of what
reality is and then what reality ought
to be and collectively you know yeah
argument was like when say the the
Christian mean Plex dominated a certain
portion of our planet you know there was
a shared is a not a shared map of
reality but now there's not rights right
and there's no kind of a agreed-upon
epistemic way to figure out what is
truthful or sort of a formula moral
formula in order to figure out what we
should do and that's obviously
problematic if we want to get along
together okay
yeah I may have initiative levels yeah I
don't know if you have any prompt
question prompts because I can go down
many different different threads with
these these crises question prompts
generally I'll just wind myself into
some sort of imaginary projected gear
don't worry though yeah but I see what
what comes up for me and these kind of
things
well these are all interrelated to some
degree right let me see what any CI can
do with this so we have a we have this
meaning crisis we have in some sense
this part of us that requires feeling
effectively involved or engaged in the
process of becoming of growth that's you
know I'm putting in a lot of my own you
know assumptions and premises here into
what I think meaning is but if you'll
allow me that meaning to be in
meaningful relationship with is to be in
something like a growth relationship
towards transformation you know and
Jordan Peterson would say something like
meaning is roughly proportional to the
responsibility you take up but I would
but that responsibility as an individual
is something that's embedded in a
collective and so your responsibility
becomes responsibility for the creation
of habitable order which can only be
understood in terms of this mesh
collective net these are all things
he'll agree with it's just that
individuals have agency within this
space so we take meaning as something
like a relationship of transfer you know
transformation and growth within self
that's in touch with reality we could
say many more things about it but let's
go with that we have the challenge of
relating this meaning-making effectively
engaged part of us with what we can
propositional II take the world to be so
they're the criteria reality crisis
given the development of culture and
this is interlinked with the proximity
crisis and globalization which you have
make note of as good fences make good
neighbors and the power of media has
flattened all social fences we have here
this need for community but and also in
some important sense we feel as though
we like we have these um we have
connections to the means of other people
around us just like that right there
there is no distance between us things
have been strangely flattened
yet we're also often we have this
feeling of isolation moving into the
sobriety crisis then we have well much
of our cognitive machinery that's
actually very helpful for us can be made
maladaptive the things we pay attention
to as salience and this is a point John
Bevere Key makes very well what we pay
attention to is salient gets into this
strange feedback loop with well it can
be co-opted right like we can we can it
can be a race to the bottom of attention
we can use things that for evolutionary
reasons trigger and just general
cognitive reasons trigger our salience
so it's like all that screens presented
really nicely that meme triggers me in
this way that face is attractive in this
way that's disgusting in that way those
words get me and that way and it glues
your attention to it and so you make the
adaptive instincts turn maladaptive due
to exposure to supernormal stimuli the
rise of the attention the economy making
us mimetic addicts and you give the
beautiful example of the the jewel
beetle the male jewel beetle confusing
aussie beer stubs with a female jewel
beetle and in trying to have sex with it
getting getting killed for long exposure
to the Sun and there's a similar thing
right we're being attracted to the wrong
things and it's it's it's it's uh it's
having us not be able to pay attention
to these other things all of these
crises kind of correlate to each other
and then that brings us one to six and
perhaps this is what we can then talk
about because all of this process all of
these difficulties we're finding
ourselves in they can be weaponized and
are being weaponized whether it's by
foreign governments whether it's by NGOs
with particular attitudes towards the
world whether it's by elites with
economic interests you know everyone
wants a piece of the pie right we are we
are being we are being manipulated this
way and that almost everywhere we go by
memes and well that's very bloody
dangerous so for this
any crisis I'll comment on the sobriety
crisis in the warfare crisis and it's
it's something that I'm wrestling with
right now cuz I recognized one of the
things that are harmful towards my
personal sovereignty and agency is
Twitter in social media right now
because it's like I find that I have to
kind of save like I'm what I'm trying to
do right now like okay only once or
twice a week I go on for 30 minutes and
that's what I'm allotted the time
allotted for right but then I find like
when I kind of like why I want to escape
whatever thing I'm doing then I go on
and it's like oh my I'm in a rabbit hole
and then I'm like crafting these these
provocative disease and I'm getting
likes on them and then I'm like you know
then you're angling your tweet like you
can be a lot more propositional II sound
you can card your premise more but like
that doesn't sound sexy enough like if I
just kind of take out this maybe end of
like would be really tired so then you
just get trapped in this this this this
kind of addictive cycle and so I feel
like I need to like really just
personally take myself away from it and
then there's just you know Connor and I
were thinking of writing this article we
were putting on a hold for now but it's
this outrage porn industrial complex
right there's like this idea of outrage
porn which is the I think we said it was
a supernormal stimuli of the culture war
right and then you know the studies have
showed that outrage causes us to want to
spread memes right and if we're
operating in a attention economy what's
gonna be encouraged in that case then if
it's the the objective is the profit
motive and is just to capture our
eyeballs is to engage an outraged porn
right because it works and then this is
a in this the idea that I'm playing with
is that our whole cult we don't have a
culture anymore right a culture is sort
of like shared values and customs that
bind us together our shared values and
custom is is engaging this outrage porno
right our culture has been replaced by
an outrage porno and is this sort of
like you know the idea of 1984 perpetual
war perpetual outrage that's what we're
engaged in like no right
and it's really making us all sort of
memetic addicts we reduced our agency
and it's a huge problem because I know
when I go down that social media
addiction cycle I'm less happy I feel
less strong I feel less powerful I'm not
bringing what I can bring forth into the
world as bad as best as I can and
there's a tremendous amount of
incentives in order for us to be these
these addicts and then this warfare
crisis is that like the this this idea
that there's unlike World War three is
already happening in a memetic landscape
right happening in the noosphere and
this is unseen battle happening in our
eyes well it's a scene battle and with
our minds our collective minds and from
like medic mercenaries that Cambridge
analytic uh from like foreign states
like Russia or China from lone wolf
hackers everyone is trying to weaponize
our minds to meet their own ends yes
right and then you got the the culture
war profiteers who you know are engaging
in outrage porn in order to make a buck
yeah and so where I like the idea that
we're all complicit in this we are all
consumers and producers of this outrage
porno yeah yeah yeah right look that the
the the the phenomenon of outrage in our
times is clearly it's self-evidently
there when you spend any amount of time
online and you know of course also when
you're in touch with what the trigger
points are for people perhaps in the
world as well but what's interesting
what's what's I think important to
stress here is that there is a oh my god
I'm gonna do this there is a
transcendent ground beneath the outrage
there is a ground of genuine human
connection and there is an inexhaustible
fount of love to tap into now
unfortunately and well necessarily that
love is wrapped around in many cases
resentment for the conditions of being
and it's a bit of a challenge whoever
gets out the
metaphysical level there's there's this
oppositional tension and you know it's
not all I'm not saying it's all roses
but the reality is is that you can walk
around and like just yesterday you know
everyday try and find these moments for
gratitude and and and unfortunate to
have many meaningful relationships in my
life and continue to pursue meaningful
interactions with people and in almost
all cases really in fact look even with
the odd schizophrenic on the street or
homeless person who for whatever reason
I come into contact with and the moment
is right for me to engage in some sort
of interaction there may be there in
some physical altercation with someone
and you can just kind of separate it a
bit or maybe just you catch you catch a
little fragment of the ramblings of
someone and it's like a little opening
for you to participate in it's like that
connection can be found all over the
place and everyone everyone's just
looking for that in so many ways and
that that place of that place of
communion that place of of coming into
right relationship with people really is
it really is there and and and we can
get lost so much in the in the
intellectualization of the conflicts we
find ourselves in and look it's not like
that isn't valid and necessary you know
I really believe it is necessary to come
to ever more keenly defined analytic
formulations of where we're at as a
culture and as individuals but there's
something about the non intellectual
embodiment of shared humanity in the
moment that is that is must always be
present for the revolutions of this
transformative cycle
of culture and of civilization and of
meaning to continue so I think that's
something worth stressing and it brings
us to a further place in conversation as
we have pretty about 10-15 minutes to go
here
which is something else I also admire a
lot about what you're doing certainly
take inspiration from well you know I
mean to be fair it's something I've also
been pursuing and I look at you as
someone who's also pursuing this and has
brought things to a different point of
articulation which I really like and you
turn one of the responses to this broad
Gestalt we've now put forward over the
last hour this this culture war 2.0
constituted by these various crises one
response as and we've sort of already
what I've already spoken about there is
a little bit as about philosophy as a
way of being and not just discourse it's
tapping into this actual embodiment of
some of this stuff but one term you use
is and we've spoken about great peeling
we've spoken about mimetic mediators
we've spoken about collective
consciousness and collective
intelligence a little bit but here's one
term it's the Hippocratic oath which you
define as values of commitment to
good-faith discourse analogous to
something like the Geneva Convention and
you do this you do this thing on your
intellectual Explorers Club podcast you
have a spoken affirmation that you take
into the conversation and as I
understand it it's your attempt to yeah
set the container right for coming into
this right relationship of discourse so
I wonder if if you can talk up a little
bit about what you mean by the
Hippocratic oath yeah
mmm you know this is timely that you ask
this question I'm gonna answer that I do
want to comment on a few things that you
mentioned that came up so I think
they're relevant and I don't want to
lose them so just to kind of close that
that thread on the outrage you know I
think outrage is a good thing and like
Aristotle talks about outrage is like a
healthy noon right and so some would
attacks
my family I'm gonna get outraged and I'm
going to defend you and I'm going to
fight that person where I want to stop
him
so when we see great evils in the world
we're gonna get outraged rightfully so
and we want to and it hopefully will
motivated us to action but I think
outrage porn makes us impotent right and
mixes doesn't make us lead to action
we're we're healthy outraged makes us
one hack and toxic out raise your
overage porn prevents action right just
like how real porn prevents sex from
occurring right it's a stimulated sex
and stimulated outrage and so I do think
outrage is good but then this current
sort of use of outrage is not healthy
the other thing that that you said what
I liked is that the kind of this
transient there transcendent kind of
component of the humanist there that
that gets lost and we can get lost in
this kind of a cup of cognitive realm
and I think it's engaging in spiritual
practices is is very important very
critical and sort of my crude or my
problem I placeholder understanding of
spirituality is overcoming the state of
disconnectedness right and is becoming
connected to the home and I actually
just want to start talking with it I
feel I don't I just got a wave of
connectedness overcoming which was
interesting but when I find when I
engage regularly in a spiritual practice
my desire to love is greater than my
desire to be loved
hmm right and I think you can you can
approach this like I'm sort of a have
perennial tendencies I think you can
approach this from various different
traditions and in experience that state
and I also would say that's having the
capacity when I'm being meta when I'm
playing the meta game and then just and
my understanding the meta game is just
taking yourself out of your own finite
game and then looking at all the finite
games non-judgmentally that when I can
get into that liminal state more often
my desire to be outraged or engage an
outraged porn becomes less and less
right so I do think maybe even being
meta in that sense is a spiritual
practice in it yes yes yes and then you
know comment on the Hippocratic oath of
the the culture war
and then know that you know that if you
have any response to what I said I'd
love to hear it when I said that's
that's timely because Connor and I
pivoted we were just kind of Conor as my
co-author he's a great collaborator with
this we're kind of like fancying
ourselves it's called true war analysts
and we're currently I don't know if
we're gonna finish it I hope we are but
we're currently writing the Hippocratic
oath of the culture were the first first
version of in gray and I just drafted
the kind of ten aspects of it and so for
the listeners who are not familiar the
Hippocratic oath is an oath that people
who engage in medicine used to take
right and it's sort of like a statement
that they read out loud in order to
ground themselves and the principle how
to be a good practitioner of medicine to
be a good doctor and people who finished
medical school still still do it in sort
of a traditional sense doesn't hold any
sort of weight as it once did but they
still still say it as sort of a
traditional oath and then the argument
they're there the flirtatious
speculation there is that if more
journalists bloggers anybody who engages
in and creating mimetic artifacts right
it's like they read this oath out loud
and then maybe they film themselves and
they have it and maybe there could be a
badge there or you can put on your blog
or your Twitter handle or something
saying that you're trying to uphold that
standard oath and the the rough draft
that were kind of creating right now is
sort of like engaging good-faith
dialogue right have intellectual
humility approach a situation that you
know I could be wrong Yeah right had
that copy out under your whatever your
statement that I could be wrong stuff
like that and so that's sort of the idea
like I'm not again it's just a playful
speculation but I think that might pick
up some steam if enough people engage in
it yeah man for sure look that's
something I've been thinking about a lot
and I haven't published anything I've
definitely written a bunch of things in
emails to different people and I have my
own draft writing on this kind of thing
just what are the values that I am
basing well that must be infused in the
community and the project
and how I am embody this whole process
and intellectual humility is one of them
there's absolutely no doubt I think I
mentioned one before this some belief in
the dignity of the human spirit and the
other one is commitment to authentic
truth seeking and it's something similar
it's like what do you take in too not
just discussion but relating in general
right what do you take into relating
with human beings that enables you to
yeah have I mean people use the terms
good faith discourse I find good faith
the good faith discourse me my I get a
little bit of a something a little dry
about it and I like Sam Harris as a man
I think he's a good dude and I think as
well he communicates very well and I
respect him the good faith dialogue
memes that surround like sam harris and
some other other guys for some reason i
find good faith dialogue good faith it's
a bit dry to me I don't know why partly
because of course there's sam harris he
died it's not like it's a bit of a
contradiction there the man doesn't
really think much of faith catechol a
brief like this this term I really like
called weaponized meta language right
it's booking why we argue or how we are
you introduced it and it's this the idea
that when you when you create a meta
language to explain a phenomena more
like something like good faith dialogue
and even though it could be
propositional e sound if a certain kind
of tribe or a certain person uses it
right and then it's it gets dirty right
yeah so it's like something you don't
want to use and so that I had the same
feeling over sort of the that term oh
yeah good face we might not use it but I
do think there's a sort of like you know
what we talked about earlier about
having the spirit of understanding
sometimes all you need even though if
you get there map of reality right yes
yes look it's cool man I think about
this stuff a lot I had a chat a
preliminary chat with Daniel Thorson of
the emerge
Podcast and are you guys recorded a
podcast recently I don't know if it's
been published or if it has but you know
we also spoke a little bit about this
together and I'll record a podcast with
Daniel I suppose over the next over the
coming months and we sort of recognized
that there are a bunch of us out there
interested in just this kind of thing
and it's important to and I'm interested
in what and we can talk about this more
off-air about what ways we can actually
collaborate to - yeah like try and try
and do this as well as possible because
well it would put into practice a lot of
the things we're talking about valuing
in many respects right this whole notion
of coming into some sort of collective
space of exploration
- yeah figure out like interesting ways
forward in in getting clear on what some
of these values are so anyway if you
would like to talk about some of that
stuff we can we can chat about it
afterwards because I do think that
getting getting that right not that it
would be final but there's a lot of
philosophy that underlies some of these
commitments right and really there's a
lot of tile discussion points to be had
there maybe I'll say this and this could
be a call to action to the listeners
right now cuz I did have a chat with
Daniel Thorson last weekend and you know
and similar with you like I feel with
Daniel there's like a Brotherhood there
yeah right there's a kinship and like I
just met Daniel I just met you but we're
all seem like we're kind of intrigued
interested by the same phenomenon and
we're kind of like riding the same way
yeah and we kind of we touch don't you
touched on this earlier like there's a
sort of informal community with a meta
modernist rallypoint Alpha rebel wisdom
all these guys are in this in the same
kind of space and there's there's
something that's occurring in Jordan
Greenhalgh John Hall is big into this
and the authentic relating movement is
big into this is this inter subjective
meditation
practice right with the call.we spaces
and having kind of a container where
dialogue once a good-faith dialogue but
dialogue can occur with these certain
values or principles and I'm wondering
out loud is if if this could if we can
create something that happens online and
digital spaces and adjacent that that
could happen in our respect it seems
right which could be scalable right so
other people can engage in this and in
other cities and the engagin and online
and I think that would be a wonderful
thing because people want to get out of
this outrage porno it doesn't lead to
happy us right it doesn't lead to ideas
yeah Yeah right look I mean I I'm
definitely open to pursuing something
like this I mean because concretely here
in Melbourne this is something I am
already doing you know I'm getting
people together I'm trying to have these
conversations whether it's after a
lecture that we watch or I think we
spoke about before or fair a couple
weeks ago about conversations at dinner
and different kinds of business models
for bringing people together for
meaningful discussion and yes I see I
see lots of ways or at least I see I see
any I see in any I feel an energy and I
think there's an importance and yeah
we'll see what comes of it but you know
we're getting close to wrapping up here
there were a couple things you mentioned
before about the the metagame
the movement to being meta and the
analogy there with respect to the
connectedness
and spirituality and the more you are in
that way of being the more you want to
give love rather than necessarily
receive it I thought that was a nice I
thought that was a nice link and I do
think that there's it's a congruent link
and there'd be plenty of things we could
we could talk about and riff on there
but I don't feel I don't feel an
incredible need to I feel yeah I feel
this has been yea really enjoyable for
me man it's been a it's been a good
conversation yeah man likewise then just
to speak on my state I feel very excited
alive in a very healthy way and I
experienced this last time we just
chatted so maybe something specific to
you that engenders this quality but
usually I get this when I land on a good
dialogue yeah man no me too and it's
what it's all about hey
so yeah dude pizza we're gonna have many
more of these conversations mate and
we'll actually hang around hang around
for just a couple minutes after this but
I will end the broadcast now actually no
I won't do you want to say anything do
you want to say anything finally about
where people can get in touch with you
or anything like that right yeah so you
can support my Twitter addiction by
following me at Peter and Limburg you
know my DMS or I think that's what you
call them are open so feel free to reach
out and chat if you want to collaborate
on anything that was mentioned here read
that the white paper follow the podcast
intellectual Explorers Club com is the
website it's on Spotify app all that
type of stuff anchor yeah that's it for
now cool man well i'll include all those
links different places and yeah one more
time thank you very much cool thank you
my friend it was a treat